[SPEAKER_01]: So, you once said that when you first came across Buddhism, you would meditate for an hour in the morning, an hour in the evening, and then... Keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you were kind of lax when it came to things like sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might go out with friends and...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, even even then, I would be sense-restrained.
[SPEAKER_02]: I wouldn't go out and then go wild or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what I was lax about, what I was not seeing, was, like, why would I go out?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would I do things I wanted to do that was within the precepts and within my meditation routine per day?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but still, why would I do these things?
[SPEAKER_02]: And it was clearly rooted in sensual desire or distraction and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I wasn't aware of that domain, not at the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was the issue there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the intentions behind my actions were covered up because I felt justified that I'm fulfilling my duty by keeping the precepts and meditating regularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the meditation was like a compensation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Afterwards, when I started questioning my motivation, regardless of how dutiful I was that day or not, I realized, well, no, but that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha didn't say, well, as long as you sit in the morning and evening, do your pujas and chores,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fine to, you know, distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: He actually didn't make all these external requirements of methods and techniques, because he said what the problem is, and if you stay there, everything else will fall into place.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I were to instead meditate in the evening, meditate in the morning for an hour and watch my nostrils and everything else, if instead I just didn't do that, but at the same time did not act out of a desire to go out and distract myself with wholesome friends,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, endure the discomfort of that desire for three days, if it lasts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's my mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's my samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would have been the direct practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would have saved me a ton of time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Until I found out later on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just through trial and error, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you don't want to admit that, if you don't want to face the unpleasantness of, you know, losing relationships or practicing celibacy, then you see this one hour in the morning and one hour in the evening as very valuable, because then you can...
[SPEAKER_02]: It keeps you grounded.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It keeps you, basically, gives you... makes you able to justify what you know deep down is a compromise.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, again, a person might be, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: Not clear about it yet, covering it up a bit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, it's a mixture of both.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, if somebody were to point it out, if they were really honest, they would say thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would see the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they don't say thank you, and if they start to double down and try to justify the method, the technique, the whatever else compensation they're doing, it's like, oh, now they're fully aware, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: That it's all rooted in weakness and a cover-up, which is now this even more habitual defense mechanism.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like a doubling down in, like, dishonesty within yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, you read just not even all the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just take a few and you will see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Acting out of desire, acting out of greed, aversion.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you spending your time of practice by keeping an eye on whether you have to do these things by body, speech and mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is your practice projected onto some sort of external level norm of behavior, routines, techniques, methods, observations, so that you don't look at the intentions behind your actions?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, there is a direct way that would have to result in the right view and liberation and that way is the way of knowing where your intentions are and not fueling them further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, yeah, peripheral, in the sense that a technique...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it is fundamentally craving...
[SPEAKER_02]: Technique is already rooted in some sort of intention that's making you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I'm desperately trying to focus on my breath or my sensations in my body, I am craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a... there is... in fact, peripheral to that is...
[SPEAKER_02]: Peripheral to that is your implicit intention that it's making you, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already making all of your actions, kind of giving them a meaning, whatever the meaning is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in this case, the meaning is, well, let me just absorb myself in it, because that's what the knowledge is, so I won't have to deal...
[SPEAKER_01]: With that vast open space of, you know, doubt, discomfort, and lack of clarity on that mental level, which is, you know, the worst feeling for somebody who is avoiding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can see why that would be popular, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because it's more palpable, more measurable, and also because it plays into all of the existing cover-ups and dishonesty.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you expect to understand your I, simply on account of the objects you're observing externally, that will never be what your I is.
[SPEAKER_02]: I is that because of which there are sights.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your consciousness can meet sights, which is elusive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then they think, oh, but if I look at someone else's eye, I learn about my eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you're learning about the organ, but you're not learning about the eye faculty, the eye that actually is a basis for vision.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, if you would even start to question that view for yourself, exactly, you're going to meet with this thick, impenetrable wall of ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, what are my senses then?
[SPEAKER_02]: This internal thing where I just get warped and distorted and filled with anxiety.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, let me just calm myself and, you know, adopt a technique, set the strict rules and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Look, look, the Buddha talks about viññāṇa all the time, so it's important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's important to be done rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not a justification.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I'll just adhere to this so I won't have to look at my intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you keep the vinaya so that you can reveal your intentions even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that elusivity is uncomfortable because...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is then elusivity, ambiguity a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it because it's not clear?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it because it's painful?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so then you assume that clarity will free you from pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So your pursuit for clarity is simply rooted in craving against pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that... And that feeds, feeds your craving further, which means, makes you liable to pain further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's ignoring this fundamental assumption that pain is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, and that, that problem, problem of aversion towards pain, and infatuation towards, with pleasure, is, is, it's like,
[SPEAKER_02]: At any given level of your experience, it's not like, oh, I need to uncover this or somewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not deeply buried.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, at the front, at the back, it's everywhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever you do, that is the guiding principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's obvious, in other way, if you were to, like, stop and look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible to have an intention like in the past or in the future.
[SPEAKER_02]: They did not go through that framework.
[SPEAKER_02]: They wasn't guided by that framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: All intentions are rooted in a desire not to suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving for pleasure, craving against pain and craving for indolence when it's neither pleasure nor pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the root of the entire universe.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha saw that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not trying to get rid of pain is where freedom from suffering lies.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding the nature... By understanding it, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, yes, people who constantly give in to their desires and have means of satisfying them, they will not become aware of the problem and pain of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they never allow time for it to really come to the fore, for them to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the longer you allow it, the more familiar you can become with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you have other people who say, okay, see, that's the problem, and then they start saying no to everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, although initially, they might have been more accurate by not engaging in sensuality, they went the other way and now overdoing saying no to everything, just again, so they wouldn't have to feel the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't have to feel the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't have to feel the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I can come on that point, the... because what a lot of people say, actually, is that, like, well, you know, it's my attachment to such and such a thing that is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I wasn't attached to such and such a thing, this experience wouldn't be painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's... that is true.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the broadest sense, that is correct, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but then, what the...
[SPEAKER_00]: It is correct, but then, what kind of... you end up sort of doing, say, okay, well, attachment...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just kind of have to give up all of my objects of attachment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, nothing will be painful for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything will be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of forgetting that the attachment to pleasure and pain is also an attachment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's only like a... as I said, in the broadest sense, that view is correct, but then, how you go about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you gave up some degree of things and to that extent you won't be bothered, but fundamentally you're attached to your sense organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, says monks, because you take what doesn't belong to you, Mahārāja can do what he wants.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is it that doesn't belong to you that you take, basically you're attached to?
[SPEAKER_02]: Eye, nose, ear,
[SPEAKER_02]: Pali tongue.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, okay, so don't take it, because that belongs to Mara, and then you'll be free.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not something you can just say no to.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where that, you know, like the other extreme of renunciation loses perspective, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, you need to renounce, say big firm no to sensual desires and engaging and acting out of anger and irritation, but
[SPEAKER_02]: That in itself, it's only like, you know, part of the picture.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you think that by saying then, cultivating the same blanket, no, even to internal states, then, again, you overshot the mark.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I keep saying, goes back to often, like, I remember even myself reading that, you know, he gets rid of the unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: How?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the Buddha says, by not welcoming, not delighting, not acting out of, by being watchful.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then all the similes of how thoughts disappear.
[SPEAKER_02]: They try to pressure you, try to make you, try to entice you to come out like a jackal to get a turtle so it can bite it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if turtle doesn't
[SPEAKER_02]: You put its limbs out of the shell, jackal loses interest and leaves, and that's how these thoughts are destroyed and got rid of.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, usually, the attitude is no, no, no to everything, and then no, no, no to my thoughts, and then double down to no, and then just complete loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: Expecting a blanket no, blanket renunciation, to work where, basically, renunciation doesn't apply.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot simply renounce your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, let me renounce these eyes, because they're not object of your attention, of your senses, which is what you can renounce.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can renounce looking at this instead of look at something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I can't renounce eyes.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as they're here, I can't renounce them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, sure enough, yeah, some people thought, oh, well, if only I don't have... if only I would not have eyes or ears, I'd be liberated.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they said, yeah, my teacher teaches not seeing forms with the eyes and not hearing things with the ears.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the liberation.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, well
[SPEAKER_02]: And then that culminates into that whole, yeah, you're still attached to avoiding pain and prolonging pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And how can you renounce that?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only train yourself out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I were to kind of question the, let's say, my meditation in the morning, in the evening, then, you know, it would mean, like, that I don't have this to fall back on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, therefore, I would have to really start giving up things that I don't want to give up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, if there was no reason, if, you know, there would be no reason to kind of avoid, to not be doing the dhamma properly, actually, if there wasn't something that you are afraid to... Well, and that's kind of the irony.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you genuinely want to do it properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know I did, from the start.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because of that kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: Careless, supposedly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cover up.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not doing it properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to do it properly, but you're going about it the wrong way, and that's why you're not doing it properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... and, like, even, let's say, somebody... you know, somebody points out, look, it's... it's the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, like, if I have to admit that this might be the wrong way,
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know if it's the case for everybody, but, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: That might mean that basically my whole, kind of, everything, this community I'm part of, this thing, this teacher I follow, like, everything that has come to almost, sort of, define my life, I might be against that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That might not be...
[SPEAKER_00]: I might have to drop all of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is really a very difficult thing to, kind of, face.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the more you have acquired,
[SPEAKER_02]: Down that path of sort of cover-up, but supposedly practice, yet just acquiring more, the harder it will then be to admit it, the harder it will be to go back and drop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's not like acting out and holding wrong views.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not a neutral thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is adding weight to the burden that you're already carrying, and it will be harder and harder to drop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you do sort of come up against this, or if you at least have like an inkling of it, and then you start admitting it to yourself, it's like this...
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I remember at one point my mind going, kind of, almost, sort of, wanting to say, please help somebody tell me what is the right thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I realized, well, look, look what you're doing, asking somebody else, looking for God, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: An external, sort of, point of clarity and authority.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then I was like, that's the whole point, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you can't... if I were to go this way and rely on this way, if I were to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't be more sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That won't make me more sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way out, then, is to... Is to not go out.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, there is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the only way out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is to admit that there is no outside of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what it boils down to.